Paul Muldoon papers, 1939-2010
Emory University
- Writings by Muldoon, circa 1960s-2004, Series 2; Boxes 8-30, 66-84 and OP 2-9, 163-167
  - Prose, 1970s-2004, Subseries 2.5; Box 29, 80-83 and OP 5-9
    - The End of the Poem: Oxford Lectures in Poetry, "'I Tried to Think a Lonelier Thing' by Emily Dickinson," typescript (Box 82, Folder 5)
    - The End of the Poem: Oxford Lectures in Poetry, "'Poem of the End' by Marina Tsvetayeva," typescript (Box 82, Folder 6)
    - The End of the Poem: "The Literary Life" by Ted Hughes (Box 82, Folder 7)
    - The Essential Byron, typescript of introduction, typescript of introduction and annotations, and typescript notes for interview on book (Box 29, Folder 27)
    - "A Forward to Irish Fairy and Folk Tales by William Butler Yeats," typescript and page proof, 2002 (Box 82, Folder 8)
    - "Getting Round: Notes Towards an Ars Poetica," The 1998 F.W. Bateson Lecture, typescripts and notes (Box 82, Folder 9)
    - "The harbor is always a mess," The Dublin Review, Winter 2000-1, proofs [See also The End of the Poem: Oxford Lectures in Poetry] (Box 82, Folder 10)
    - "The Influence of Cinema on Contemporary Irish Poetry," typescript (Box 82, Folder 11)
    - "In the Hall of Mirrors: 'Autopsychography' by Fernando Pessoa," New England Review, Vol. 23 no. 4, proofs, October 2002 (Box 82, Folder 12)
    - "Madoc: A Mystery," introduction to dramatic reading of the poem, corrected typescript (Box 29, Folder 28)
    - Muldoon Poetry Reading, Irish Seminar, Dublin, July 28, 2003, typescript of comments about poems with introduction by Seamus Deane (Box 82, Folder 13)
    - "Paul Muldoon on John Donne's '[Show me, dear Christ, Thy spouse, so bright and clear],'" typescript (Box 82, Folder 14)
    - "Poetry and School," University College Dublin, Millennium Lecture Series, 2000, typescript (Box 82, Folder 15)
    - "The Point of Poetry," typescript draft with holograph corrections and final uncorrected typescript draft (Box 29, Folder 29)
    - "Polar Expeditions: 'I Tried To Think a Lonelier Thing' by Emily Dickinson," New England Review vol. 24 no. 2, proofs, April 2003 [See also The End of the Poem: Oxford Lectures in Poetry] (Box 82, Folder 16)
    - Queen's University, Belfast, Honorary Degree acceptance speech, typescripts (Box 82, Folder 17)
    - "Rara Avis," typescripts (Box 82, Folder 18)
    - Remarks, 2001 T.S. Eliot Prize Announcement (Box 82, Folder 19)
    - "Stiff Little Fingers: 'Alternative Ulster,'" typescript (Box 83, Folder 1)
    - "Talk of the Town," typescript, September 2001 (Box 83, Folder 2)
    - To Ireland, I, corrections and proofs, 1999-2000 (Box 83, Folder 3)
    - To Ireland, I, index, typescript (Box 83, Folder 4)
    - To Ireland, I: The 1998 Clarendon Lectures, "Contaygious to the Nile," typescript (Box 83, Folder 5)
    - To Ireland, I: The 1998 Clarendon Lectures, typescript (Box 83, Folder 6)
    - "Whitman, Yeats and Joyce," typescript with minimal holograph corrections (Box 29, Folder 30)
    - Why Brownlee Left, clipping of note from Poetry Book Society journal, Autumn 1980 (Box 29, Folder 31)
    - "Why Poetry Should be Taught at the Secondary Level," UNESCO, typescript and notes, circa 2000-2001 (Box 83, Folder 7)
    - "Yeats and Politics," mixed typescript and photocopies of Yeats poems with holograph notes, all in in yellow binder with brochure for Arts and Letters Live 1994 season (Box 29, Folder 32)
    - Untitled autobiographical sketch, typescript (Box 29, Folder 33)
    - Unidentified Lecture on "Getting Around," January, 1998 (Box 83, Folder 8)
    - Untitled essay on Louis MacNeice's "Autumn Journal," typescript (Box 83, Folder 9)
    - Untitled statement on listening to lectures, typescript (Box 83, Folder 10)
    - Untitled typescript about the relationship between poetry and the Troubles (Box 83, Folder 11)
    - Unidentified lecture and essay notes (Box 83, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified typescript fragment (Box 83, Folder 13)
  - Notebooks, Subseries 2.6; Boxes 30 and 84
    The subseries consists of notebooks kept by Muldoon which include early drafts of poems and other writings.
    - Mead Composition, 2 pp. holograph notes (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Mead Composition, 31 pp. holograph notes (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Eaton pad, 5 pp. holograph notes (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Blue hardcover, holograph note "Muldoon / Japan / September- / October / 1994" inside front cover, circa 18 pp. holograph notes (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Red and black hardcover, 4 pp. holograph notes with insertion of multiple corrected typescript drafts of "Between Takes" (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Blue exercise book, 18pp of holograph notes (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Der Grüne Block, graph paper notebook, circa 1995 (Box 84, Folder 1)
    - Orange and yellow hardcover, circa 2000 (Box 84, Folder 2)
  - Belfast group sheets, Subseries 2.7; Box 30
    The subseries contains the copied typescripts of poems written and work-shopped by members of the Belfast Group during their meetings. The group sheets featured in this subseries include poems by Paul Muldoon (for other Belfast Group Sheets, also see related collections).
    - Group Sheet 1: 2 leaves, 4 sides, 4 copies: includes "Wind and Tree," "Hedges in Winter," "Cuckoo Corn," "Siesta," "Vampire," "Grass Window," "The Indians on Alcatraz," and "The Electric Orchard" (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - Group Sheet 2: 3 leaves, 5 sides, 7 copies: includes "Stillborn," "Snail," "January," "Poem at Eighteen," "Hawk," "Hedgehog," "Seanchas," "Unborn," "Leaving the Island" (dated "Lough Derg 1969") (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - Group Sheet 3: 2 leaves, 4 sides: includes, "Blowing Eggs," "The Radio Horse," "On A Dog of Unlike Eyes," "The Lost Tribe," "The Upriver Incident," "Party Piece" (Box 30, Folder 9)
- Writings by others, 1939-2004, Series 3; Boxes 31-34, 85-89 and OP 10-11
  The series consists writings by others sent to Paul Muldoon from 1939-2004. The series includes works from poets such as Seamus Heaney, Ciaran Carson, Michael Longley and Tess Gallagher, as well as unpublished theses and critical studies on Muldoon's work. The series also includes a discussion on poetry between Louis MacNeice and F. R. Higgins from 1939 with notes written in the margins by Muldoon, as well as materials relating to published interviews with Muldoon.
  Organized into two subseries: (3.1) Poetry and (3.2) Theses and unpublished articles, essays, and interviews.
  - Poetry, 1978-2004, Subseries 3.1; Boxes 31, 85 and OP 10-11
    The subseries consists of poems written by other authors from 1978-2004, including Seamus Heaney, Ciaran Carson, Michael Longley and Tess Gallagher. Most files include an unpublished typescript, and some files include notes and supplementary art work.
    Arranged in alphabetical order by author.
    - Badilla, Sergio, Selected Poems, circa 23 pp. with color art cover page (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Carson, Ciaran, uncorrected typescripts of "At the Ulster Hall.. ." and "The Riddle of the Sands," with 27 pp. typescript of Letters From the Alphabet with minimal holograph corrections, July 25, 1994 - August 25, 1994 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Carson, Ciaran, The Alexandrine Plan, uncorrected typescript translations, circa 1998 (Box 85, Folder 1)
    - Donnelly, Susan, "Paul Muldoon Sneaks in a Sestina," circa November 2002 (Box 85, Folder 2)
    - Entries to the W.B. Yeats Society of New York Poetry Competition, 2001, including winning entry, "Study (with Ocean)" by Cameron Gearen, second prize winning entry, "At the Merchant's House," by Zoe Anglessey and honorable mentions by unidentified authors (Box 85, Folder 3)
    - Gallagher, Tess, typescripts of "You Talk on Your Telephone; I Talk on Mine," "Second Sleep," "Crepes Flambeau," "The Wives of My Childhood" (with holograph corrections), "I Take Care of You: A Lantern Dashes By in the Grass," "The Hands of the Blindman," "I Save Your Coat But You Lose It Later," "Bird-Window-Flying," "Some With Wings, Some With Manes" (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - Haas, Philip and Belinda, Angels and Insects bound script, based on the novella by A.S. Byatt, November 30, 1993 (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - Heaney, Seamus, typescripts of "Among the Whins" (with minimal holograph corrections), "Chekov on Sakhalin," "Country Roads" (with holograph corrections), "The Death of Orpheus" (photocopy with holograph corrections, "unfinished"), "The Easter House," "A Hazel Stick for My Daughter," "Holly," "In a Yard," and "Remembering Malibu" (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Heaney, Seamus, typescript of "The Chestnut Tree" (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Heaney, Seamus, typescript of sections from "Crossings" (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - Heaney, Seamus, typescript of "Lightenings" (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - Heaney, Seamus, "The Midnight Verdict" (An abridged version of "Cuirt and Mhean Oiche" (1780) from the Irish of Brian Merriman), photocopy of typescript with holograph corrections (Box 31, Folder 9)
    - Heaney, Seamus, "Orpheus and Eurydice," photocopy of typescript with holograph corrections (Box 31, Folder 10)
    - Heaney, Seamus, photocopy packet of mostly Spirit Level poems: including "The Rainstick," "To a Dutch Potter in Ireland," "Mint," "A Sofa in the Forties," "Keeping Going," "Diptych," "Poet's Chair," "At Banagher," and "Postscript" (Box 31, Folder 11)
    - Heaney, Seamus, photocopied typescript of [The Spirit Level] (Box 31, Folder 12)
    - Heaney, Seamus, photocopy packet of "Sweeney Astray," "Station Island," "Chekhov on Sakhalin," and "Home From Home," circa 35 typescript pages in manila folder (Box 31, Folder 13)
    - Heaney, Seamus, typescript of "Ugolino" (Box 31, Folder 14)
    - Heaney, Seamus, typescript of "A Villanelle for Marie," "A Kite for Michael and Christopher," "A Hank of Wool," "A Cart for Edward Gallagher," "A Deer in Glanmore," "Near Anahorish: A Visitation," "New Worlds," and "Late Offerings" (Box 31, Folder 15)
    - Heaney, Seamus, Broadside (#95 of 100) of poem "Mint," inscribed "For Paul and Jean, with love, June 13, 1991" [pulled and cataloged in literary broadsides, 23 April 2008] (Box OP10)
    - Heaney, Seamus, galley proof, Beowulf: A New Translation, circa 2001 (Box 85, Folder 4)
    - Heaney, Seamus, galley proof, The Haw-Lantern, 1987 (Box 85, Folder 5)
    - Heaney, Seamus, typescripts, "The Spot" and "Sophoclean," 2003 (Box 85, Folder 6)
    - Heaney, Seamus, typescript fragment, "The Yellow Bittern," translation from Cathal Bui Mac Giolla Ghunna, 1996 (Box 85, Folder 7)
    - Houston, Peyton, "Images of the Garden" and "Importance of the Unicorn," pamphlet from The Hudson Review (Box 31, Folder 16)
    - Kantor, Peter, photocopy packet of poems: includes "Beginning," "History," "As in a Cartoon Film," "Somewhere between the Budapest Hilton and a Liverpool Dock," "Follow Me," "What Do You Need to be Happy?" "On the Curb," "Inventory," "On a Jang Ci-June Saying," "Colour Beginning," "After the Coal-Stoppage," "Grandmother," "And Slowly Everything Took On a Different Shape," "Ayala," and "Encounter" (Box 31, Folder 17)
    - Keeley, Edmund, "The Man from Chios Called Homer," typescript translation from Semonides, 2004 (Box 85, Folder 8)
    - Lewin, Marla, "The Voice of Paul Muldoon," typescript with holograph note (Box 31, Folder 18)
    - Lishan, Stuart, The Body Bestiary, circa 56 pages spiral bound typescript with holograph note on cover page (Box 31, Folder 19)
    - Longley, Edna, "Capercaillies," unpublished typescript, 1998 (Box 85, Folder 9)
    - [Longley, Michael (?)], typescripts of "Communications" (signed and dated April 4, 1979) and "Home Ground" (signed and dated May 2,1978) (Box 31, Folder 20)
    - Longley, Michael, "Two Skunks," typescript, August 2001 (Box 85, Folder 10)
    - Lumbbank Poetry Anthology, edited by Michael Longley and Paul Muldoon, June 1985 (Box 31, Folder 28)
    - MacNeice, Louis, photocopied typescripts, "The Candlestick Maker," "Untitled," and "Ad Infinitum," no date (Box 85, Folder 11)
    - McGahern, John, typescripts of "The Beginning of an Idea" (21 pages) and "Doorways" (15 pages) (Box 31, Folder 21)
    - McSweeney, Joyelle, typescript, "Tea-Strainer," no date (Box 85, Folder 12)
    - [Montague, John (?)], "II: Peephole," typescript with single holograph correction (Box 31, Folder 22)
    - Ní Dhomhnaill, Nuala, "Finnegan Redivivus: The Corpse Talks Back," circa 15 page typescript of essay, with photocopy of poem "The Language Issue" (original Irish and Muldoon's translation) in Pharoh's Daughter (Box 31, Folder 23)
    - Parcerisas, Francesc, translations into Catalan of Muldoon poems from Quoof and Meeting the British, 2004 (Box 85, Folder 13)
    - Unidentified, 2 drawings of Muldoon, one dated May 16, 1987 (Box 31, Folder 24)
    - Unidentified, "Carmen et Error," corrected typescript [possibly Muldoon] (Box 31, Folder 25)
    - Unidentified, "Mother Coats" and "Bridge Means" (Box 31, Folder 26)
    - Unidentified, "Rinsings civ," photocopy of typescript (Box 31, Folder 27)
    - Unidentified, "Come to me, if you are ailing.. ." holograph poem on cardboard (Box OP11)
    - Unidentified author, "Aeriel," typescript, no date (Box 85, Folder 14)
    - Unidentified author, "Portrait" and "the Virgin at the Window," typescripts (Box 85, Folder 15)
    - Unidentified author, "Prized," typescript, no date (Box 85, Folder 16)
  - Theses and unpublished articles, essays, and interviews, 1939-2004, Subseries 3.2; Boxes 32-34, 86-89
    The subseries consists primarily of writings about Muldoon's poetry from approximately 1987-2004, including theses, unpublished articles, and essays, as well as transcripts of interviews with Muldoon. Most files contain an original copy of the essay, article, or interview, with some files containing accompanying correspondence and cover letters. The subseries also includes a discussion on poetry between Louis MacNeice and F. R. Higgins from 1939 with notes written in the margins by Muldoon
    - Allen, Michael, typescript, "Pax Hibernica / Pax Americana: Rhyme and Reconciliation in Muldoon," no date (Box 86, Folder 1)
    - Barker, Sebastian, interview, "A Drink with Paul Muldoon," Long Group Poem Newsletter, typescripts and correspondence, 1997-1998 (Box 86, Folder 2)
    - Barron, Patrick, typescript of interview with Muldoon with extensive holograph comments, answers, and corrections by Muldoon, with cover letter to P. Barron, August 31, 1994 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - Batten, Guinn, "Belfast Crack: Ciaran Carson's Parturient Partition," typescript of March 1992 Graduate Student Conference in Irish Studies paper (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Batten, Guinn, "Dissent and Descent: Paul Muldoon's Family Romances," typescript essay, March 25, 1992, with cover letter (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - Batten, Guinn, The Orphaned Imagination: Home, Loss, and Melancholia in English Romantic Poetry," typescript of dissertation proposal with cover letter to Muldoon, July 1, 1992 [sic-93] (Box 32, Folder 4)
    - Batten, Guinn, "Romantic Melancholy and Contemporary Irish Poetry" (paper delivered at ACIS panel, 1993 MLA Conference) and "Professional Mourning and Poetic Melancholy" (preface to The Orphaned Imagination) both typescript essays enclosed with cover letter to Muldoon, April 28, 1994 (Box 32, Folder 5)
    - Batten, Guinn, "Where All the Ladders Start: Identity, Ideology, and the Ghosts of the Subjected Body in Blake, Yeats and Muldoon," typescript, no date (Box 86, Folder 3)
    - Bellamy, Dawn, "'All would be swept away'? Generic development in Paul Muldoon's 'Yarrow,'" draft of Masters dissertation, September 2001 (Box 86, Folder 4)
    - Benedetti, Sandrine, Paul Muldoon: Some Aspects of His Poetry, bound Master's thesis for Universite de Caen, Department of English and North American Studies, 1987 (Box 32, Folder 6)
    - Bern, Megan, bachelors thesis, "'Singleminded Swervings,' Thematic Consideration by Volume of the Early Poetry of Paul Muldoon," 1997 (Box 86, Folder 5)
    - Birkerts, Sven, "millennium questionnaire," interview with typed responses by Paul Muldoon, January 4, 2000 (Box 86, Folder 6)
    - Blacking, John, "Myths About Man and Society," typescript (Box 32, Folder 7)
    - Bosch, Daniel, "Outpost of Progressivism," review of Madoc: A Mystery (Box 32, Folder 8)
    - Bolman, Christopher, typescript, "Communicating through Chaos: An Interpretation of the Inner Workings of Paul Muldoon's 'Symposium,'" May 12, 2003 (Box 86, Folder 7)
    - Brandes, Randy, typescript of interview with Seamus Heaney at Emory University Ellmann Lectures (April 1988) (Box 32, Folder 9)
    - Breeze, Andrew, The Magic of Poetry was Transformation; It was Words Changing Shape, Meaning and Form, no date (Box 86, Folder 8)
    - Bruton, John, untitled lecture typescript on the Irish peace process, delivered September 25, 2001 (Box 86, Folder 9)
    - Burt, Steve, typescript of Harvard University Bachelor's thesis chapter on Muldoon, with cover letter "November 13, 1993" (Box 32, Folder 10)
    - Buxton, Rachel, Never Quite Showing His Hand: Robert Frost and Paul Muldoon, no date (Box 86, Folder 10)
    - Cliff, Brian, biographical entry on Muldoon, unidentified publication, circa 2003 (Box 86, Folder 11)
    - Cliff, Brian, doctoral dissertation, Communities of Difference in Contemporary Irish Literature, 2001 (Box 86, Folder 12)
    - Cliff, Brian, Poetry "On the Cusp": The Manuscripts for Paul Muldoon's "7, Middagh Street," December 16, 1997 (Box 86, Folder 13)
    - Cliff, Brian, interview with Muldoon, corrected transcript, no date (Box 86, Folder 14)
    - Contemporary Authors, biographical sketch of Muldoon included in the volume, corrected proof, February 1996 (Box 87, Folder 1)
    - Corcoran, Neil, "A Languorous Cutting Edge: Muldoon vs. Heaney?", typescript, no date (Box 87, Folder 2)
    - Corcoran, Neil, typescripts and page proof of interview conducted with Muldoon at the 2000 Ulster Symposium, 2000-2004 (Box 87, Folder 3)
    - Coulter, Anne, The Poetry of Paul Muldoon, spiral-bound Bachelor's thesis for Ulster Polytechnic, 1984 (Box 32, Folder 11)
    - Crofts, Thomas, Neither One Thing or the Other: Metamorphosis as a Key to the Poetry of Paul Muldoon, typescript M.Phil. thesis for Trinity College, Dublin, 1992, with typescript of provisional outline (Box 32, Folder 12)
    - Drum, Meredith, interview with Muldoon, July 11, 1997 (Box 87, Folder 4)
    - Editors, Lily. A Monthly Online Literary Review, typescript interview with Muldoon, December 17, 2003 (Box 87, Folder 5)
    - Farrimond, Patrick, "Going with the Flow: Paul Muldoon and the Loss of Aesthetic Duty," no date (Box 87, Folder 6)
    - Gales, Christopher. Interview with Paul Muldoon (1980's?). (Box 32, Folder 13)
    - Gaudin, Elisabeth and Jacues Jouet, typescript packet of translations of 12 Quoof poems with several pieces of correspondence, including Muldoon's responses to their questions (Box 32, Folder 14)
    - Gauthier, Dominique, typescript essay, "'The Big House' by Paul Muldoon: The Approach of the Satirist," circa 1994 (Box 87, Folder 7)
    - Gauthier, Dominique, typescript article, "Thèmes et variations: les mythologies américaines subversives du poète Paul Muldoon," February 1996 (Box 87, Folder 8)
    - Gauthier, Dominique, typescript of interview with Muldoon, February 1996 (Box 87, Folder 9)
    - Gering, August, To Sing of '98: The United Irishmen Rising and the Ballad Tradition in Heaney and Muldoon, summer, 1999 (Box 87, Folder 10)
    - Greenlaw, Lavinia, typescripts of interview with Muldoon, November 2000-March 2001 (Box 87, Folder 11)
    - Haffenden, John, conversation with Paul Muldoon (revised), no date (Box 87, Folder 12)
    - Hall, Donald; McHugh, Heather; Huntington, Cynthia; Muldoon, Paul; Simic, Charles; page proofs and corrections by Muldoon of transcribed discussion, published in Harpers Magazine, 1999 (Box 87, Folder 13)
    - Hart, Michael, typescript of Muldoon's entry in Modern Irish Writers: A Bio-critical Sourcebook, with cover letter August 21, 1995 (Box 32, Folder 15)
    - Hartley, George, typescript, "Rewriting the Conquest: The Poetics of Hegemony in Francisco X. Alarcón," no date (Box 87, Folder 14)
    - Heaney, Seamus, "The Poetry of Richard Murphy," offprint (Box 32, Folder 16)
    - Jones, Rodney, Ed Brunner, and Charles Fanning, Paul Muldoon interview, April 21, 1995 (Box 87, Folder 15)
    - Keane, Patrick, "The Colereidgean 'One Life' in Muldoon's Madoc," typescript essay (Box 32, Folder 17)
    - Kendall, Tim, typescript of chapter on Annals, with bibliography fragments and acknowledgements draft (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Kendall, Tim, typescript of chapter on The Prince of the Quotidian and Six Honest Serving Men (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - Kendall, Tim, early typescript of Paul Muldoon, with cover letter June 25, 1995 (1 of 2) (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - Kendall, Tim, early typescript of Paul Muldoon (2 of 2) (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - Kendall, Tim, "Fathers and Mothers: On Paul Muldoon's Life," typescript chapter (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - Kendall, Tim, "Paul Muldoon and the Art of Allusion," typescript (Box 33, Folder 6)
    - Kendall, Tim, "Paul Muldoon's 'Singleminded Swervings'" typescript of thesis chapter on Muldoon, with cover letter May 9, 1994 (Box 33, Folder 7)
    - Ketteridge, Rob, script for television special, "Coming to Terms: Ireland, Artists and the Peace Process," featuring Muldoon, circa 2000 (Box 87, Folder 16)
    - Koch, Kenneth, "About Paul Muldoon," no date (Box 87, Folder 17)
    - Kosters, Onno, "Making the Translation: vier vertalers op zoek naar een vertaling," bound typescript thesis in Dutch for Vrije University, Amsterdam, with cover letter June 17, 1990 (Box 33, Folder 8)
    - Lloyd, Christian L., The Crisis of Style: The Poetry of Paul Muldoon, hardcover bound Master's thesis for University of Saskatchewan, with photocopy abstract, October 1990 (Box 33, Folder 9)
    - McCarey, Peter, "How Duke Valentine Contrived," typescript, no date (Box 87, Folder 18)
    - McCurry, Jackie, Serious Mischief: Paul Muldoon's Poetry, typescript of unpublished book with cover letter November 4, 1994 [1 of 2] (Box 33, Folder 10)
    - McCurry, Jackie, Serious Mischief: Paul Muldoon's Poetry, typescript of unpublished book [2 of 2] (Box 33, Folder 11)
    - McCurry, Jacqueline, untitled typescript (Box 87, Folder 19)
    - McDonald, Peter, typescript of book chapter, "Paul Muldoon and the windlass-men," from Mistaken Identities: Poetry and Northern Ireland, 1997 (Box 87, Folder 20)
    - Mac Giolla Léith, Caoimhín, "Translating Contemporary Irish Poetry Into English: The Case of Nuala Ní Dhomhnaill," photocopy of typescript with holograph corrections (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - McGrath, Niall, typescript of interview with Paul Muldoon at the John Hewitt International Festival, Co. Antrim, July 29, 1994 (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - MacNeice, Louis and F. R. Higgins, " 'Tendencies in Modern Poetry,' a discussion broadcast from Northern Ireland," The Listener, 1939 (with Muldoon's handwritten notes) (Box 34, Folder 2a)
    - Martin, Richard, typescript, preface to Muldoon translation of The Birds, circa 1999 (Box 87, Folder 21)
    - Muldoon, Maureen, untitled novel, typescript, circa 2005 [1 of 2] (Box 88, Folder 1)
    - Muldoon, Maureen, untitled novel, typescript, circa 2005 [2 of 2] (Box 88, Folder 2)
    - Murphy, Shane, "Obliquity in the Poetry of Paul Muldoon and Medbh McGuckian," typescript, April 1997 (Box 88, Folder 3)
    - Ni Dhomhnaill, Nuala, "A Ghostly Alhambra," unidentified translator, circa 1997 (Box 88, Folder 4)
    - Noble, Jennifer, typescript of 1990 interview with Muldoon at Yeats Summer School, with two cover letters (Box 34, Folder 3)
    - Ohno, Mitsuko, "In Different Voices: Contemporary Irish Woman Poets and Japan," offprint of essay on Nuala Ní Dhomhnaill's Pharoh's Daughter, March 1995 (Box 34, Folder 4)